<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Alternate-Leaf Dogwood</Name>
    <OtherName>Pagoda Dogwood</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Cornus alternifolia</ScientificName>
    <Description>It is a small deciduous tree growing to 25' rarely 30' tall, with a trunk up to 6" in diameter. The branches develop characteristic horizontal layers separated by gaps, with a flat-topped crown.</Description>
    <Leaves>Elliptic to ovate and grow to 2" – 5" long and 1" – 2" broad, arranged alternately on the stems, not in opposite pairs typical of the majority of Cornus species. The leaves are most often arranged in crowded clusters around the ends of the twigs and appear almost whorled. The upper sides of the leaves are smooth and green, while the undersides are hairy and a bluish color.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Yellowish to purplish green, smooth, tips curved upward; terminal buds, light brown, 2 scales, pointed tip.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Drupe, globular, blue-black, 5/16" across, tipped with remnant of style which rises from a slight depression; nut obovoid, many-grooved.  Mature in mid autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Dark reddish brown, with shallow ridges. Branchlets at first pale reddish green, later dark green.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  Eastern North America, from Newfoundland west to southern Manitoba and Minnesota, and south to northern Florida and Mississippi. It is rare in the southern United States.</Range>
    <Remarks>Shade-tolerant; slow to moderately growing; short-lived.  Common understory species usually found in association with maples and basswoods.  With the exception of alternate leaf dogwood, all other dogwoods can be identified by their leaves, which have distinctly curved lateral veins that tend to parallel the margins, and by their opposite buds, which have two scales.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AlternateLeafDogwood/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AlternateLeafDogwood/UpClose1.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AlternateLeafDogwood/Seed.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AlternateLeafDogwood/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AlternateLeafDogwood/Seedling.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>