<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>American Plum</Name>
    <OtherName>Wild plum, river plum, sandhill plum</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Prunus americana</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shrub or small tree 3' - 24' tall, and are usually forming thickets.  The small branches are sometimes spiny.  Trunk up to 10" in diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, egg-shaped to oval, 2" - 4" long, 1 1/4" - 2" wide.  The upper leaf surface is shiny green and the lower surface is slightly hairy; leaf margins are sharply toothed.  Golden yellow in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Light brown to green, and sometimes hairy.  They have a distict bitter almond smell when broken in two with thornlike spur shoots often present on the branchlets.  Thorns will be rough with buds or leaves attached.  The buds are red-brown.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Drupe, red to yellow, almost globular edible plums about l" in diameter.  Mature in late summer.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Red-brown to dark brown or grayish, becoming scaly with age; its branches are more or less spiny with sharp-tipped twigs.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  The range is from Massachusetts west to Manitoba and Montana, south to Utah, Colorado, and Oklahoma, east to Florida, and north to New York.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowers are white, 5-petaled, about 1 inch across, and borne singly or in clusters at the juncture of a stem and leaf.  American plum is highly important as wildlife cover and food.  The thorny, suckering growth, when protected, forms a thicket valuable for bird nesting, loafing, and roosting, and animal loafing and bedding.  Twigs and foliage provide a highly preferred browse for whitetail and mule deer.  The thorny growth and suckering characteristics should be considered before planting this species near a recreation area.  It can be used for screening and natural barriers.  The fruit is used widely for making jams and jellies.  American plum was and still is used as a source of food and medicine by Native Americans in the Midwest and West.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanPlum/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanPlum/Fruit.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanPlum/Flowers.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanPlum/Seedling.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanPlum/Trees.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>