<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Amercian Linden</Name>
    <OtherName>American Basswood/White Basswood</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Tilia americana</ScientificName>
    <Description>Large trees, 50' - 90' tall; thick, broad, round or egg-shaped crown with drooping branches.  Trunk can grow to 3' in diameter and may sound hollow when you hit it.</Description>
    <Leaves>Deciduous, alternate, unevenly heart-shaped or the base often nearly truncate, petiolate, the blades 2" - 5" wide, thick and leathery, with sharp coarsely toothed margins, smooth on top with some hairs possible on the lower surface.  Yellow-green; turning yellow to orange in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red-gray to dark gray with red or green buds, slimy when crushed.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Clusters of drupes attached to a oblong, leaflike bract.  Matures in autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Smooth gray becoming dark gray and furrowed with flat vertical ridges.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  Native to the Northern Deciduous and Great Lakes - St. Lawrence forest regions of North America.  It also extends into grassland areas along river courses in Manitoba and the mid-western United States, where it forms a component of riverine gallery forests.  In Canada, it is found from western New Brunswick into southern and central Québec and Ontario, extending as far west as north-western Ontario (along the U.S. border) and southern Manitoba.  In the United States, the species occurs as far south as the mountainous regions of North Carolina, Tennessee, and northern Arkansas.  The western limit for the species is south-central Manitoba and North Dakota, and along the Niobrara River in north-central Nebraska.</Range>
    <Remarks>Native Americans and settlers used the fibrous inner bark ("bast") as a source of fiber for rope, mats, fish nets, and baskets.  Basswood is still valued for its soft, light, easily worked wood, especially for turned items and hand carving.  Basswood is good browse and buds are important for birds and deer in winter.  Fruits are eaten by birds and small mammals.  The wood decays easily and produces many cavities (especially in trees past 120 years of age), which are used by cavity-nesting animals (wood ducks, pileated woodpeckers, other birds, and small mammals).  Basswood is a prolific nectar producer and pollination by honeybees results in a choice grade of honey.  Flowers yellowish-white.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanLinden/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanLinden/Leaf.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanLinden/Fruit.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanLinden/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/AmericanLinden/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>