<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Black Locust</Name>
    <OtherName>False acacia, Yellow locust</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Robinia pseudoacacia</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree, 30' - 60' tall; open, irregular crown; has a shallow, aggressive root system with the trunk up to 24" diameter, often crooked.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, pinnately compound leaves are 8" to 14" long, with 7 - 19 short stalked leaflets.  These dull green leaflets are ovoid or oval, 1" - 2" long, 1/2" - 3/4" wide, scabrous above and pale below.  Yellow in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Lateral buds, reddish-brown, 3 or more sunken in leaf scar, hairy.  Alternate branching pattern, which creates a zigzag effect.  A pair of sharp thorns grows at each node.  They are 1/2" to 3/4" long, and very stout.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Legume type seed is produced in a flat, brown to black pod, which is 2" - 4" inches long.  There is an average of 25,500 seeds per pound.  Although black locust is a good seed producer, its primary means of spread is by both rudimentary and adventitious root suckers.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Deeply furrowed and is dark reddish-brown to black in color with orangish troughs.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3b.  Native range follows the Appalachian Mountains from Pennsylvania to Alabama, and a secondary population exists primarily in the Ozark Mountains.  Black locust is adapted to a wide variety of soil types, but grows best on sites that are deep, well drained, and derived from limestone.  This tree tolerates a pH range of 4.6 to 8.2.  It is commonly found on south and west slopes in West Virginia.</Range>
    <Remarks>Sweetly fragrant flowers that are creamy white with five petals.  They usually bloom in May or June.  The wood of black locust is strong, hard, and extremely durable, it is extensively utilized for fencing, mine timbers, and landscaping ties.  This tree also serves as a good erosion control plant on critical and highly disturbed areas, due to its ease of establishment, rapid early growth and spread, and soil building abilities.  This plant is considered noxious and/or invasive in some states.  This plant may become weedy or invasive in some regions or habitats and may displace desirable vegetation if not properly managed.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackLocust/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackLocust/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackLocust/Flower.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackLocust/Fruit.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackLocust/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>