<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Black Ash</Name>
    <OtherName>Basket Ash</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Fraxinus nigra</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree growing 29' - 59' tall.  Ascending branches, narrow crown, and slender trunk (18") sometimes bent or leaning.</Description>
    <Leaves>Deciduous, opposite, 6" - 16" long, pinnately compound with 7 - 11 oval to lance-shaped leaflets each 4" - 5 1/2" long, 1" - 2" wide with finely toothed margins, dark green above, lighter green beneath with some rusty hairs, turning purple to brown in the fall.  The terminal leaflet has a short stalk, but the other leaflets are attached directly to the leaf stalk (petiole).</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Light green to gray with light brown lenticels (dots), bluish to black buds.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Winged nutlets (samaras) 1" - 1 3/4" long and 1/8" wide.  Blunt at both ends, winged to the base, borne in terminal or axillary clusters, the clusters hanging at maturity.  Fruiting: June-September dispersed: July-October.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray, becoming corky-ridged and shallowly furrowed, divided into large irregular plates with thin, papery scales that rub off easily.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 3a.  Black ash is native to the Great Lakes and Acadia regions of North America, in southeastern Canada from Newfoundland to eastern Manitoba, south to Iowa, Illinois, West Virginia, and Virginia.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowering: May-June, with the leaves or just before.  Flowers are small, purplish, usually in clusters near the branch tips.  Uses:  Basketry splint, barrel hoops, snowshoe frames, canoe ribs, and material for woven chair seats.  Black ash is an important tree for the making of lacrosse sticks used by the Mohawk and other tribes of the Eastern United States.  The winged seeds are eaten by a number of birds including wood ducks, quail, bobwhite, purple finches, and pine grosbeaks.  Mammals also eat the seeds including beaver, porcupines, and white-footed mice.  Black ash most commonly grows in moist to wet muck or shallow organic soils, especially in swamps, floodplains, terraces, ravines, and on small, poorly drained upland pockets.  It also may grow on sands and loams with high water tables.  It can tolerate standing water for many weeks, but best growth is on better-drained sites.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackAsh/CloseUp.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackAsh/Buds.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackAsh/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackAsh/Leaves.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackAsh/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>