<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Common Buckthorn</Name>
    <OtherName>Purging Buckthorn</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Rhamnus cathartica</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shrub or small tree that can grow to 22' in height and have a trunk up to 10" wide. The crown shape of mature plants is spreading and irregular.</Description>
    <Leaves>Opposite and occasionally alternate; 1" - 2 1/4" long, 3/4" - 2" wide, broadly oval, rounded or pointed at the tip, with 3-4 pairs of upcurved veins, and have jagged, toothed margins. The upper and lower leaf surfaces are without hairs. Leaves appear dark, glossy green on the upper surface and stay green late into fall, after most other deciduous leaves have fallen.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Gray, stubby-spur shoots, usually spine tipped; buds, brown, fuzzy scale tips.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Globose black drupe 5/16" diameter containing two to four seeds, mature in autumn; it is mildly poisonous for people, but readily eaten by birds, which disperse the seeds in their droppings.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray to brown, rough textured when mature and may be confused with that of plum trees in the genus Prunus. When cut, the inner bark is yellow and the heartwood, pink to orange.</Bark>
    <Range>Native to Europe, northwest Africa, and western Asia, from the central British Isles south to Morocco, and east to Kyrgyzstan. It was introduced to North America as an ornamental shrub in the early 19th century or perhaps before.</Range>
    <Remarks>Shade-tolerant, moderately fast-growing and short-lived. This species is a tough, durable tree which adapts to urban or suburban environments, and virtually any area it is dispersed in. It is widely regarded as a major invasive species whose shade prevents the establishment of native trees or shrubs. It has become the target of efforts to eradicate it from home sites, parks and woodland areas. It is difficult to control because it sprouts vigorously and repeatedly from the root collar following cutting, girdling, or burning, though it can be controlled by applying concentrated herbicide to the cut stem.  Some around my home town of Rochester, MN believe that the Mayo brothers may have brought it to this area for use on their farms :)</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonBuckthorn/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonBuckthorn/UpClose1.png</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonBuckthorn/Fruit.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonBuckthorn/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonBuckthorn/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>