<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Common Prickly-Ash</Name>
    <OtherName>Toothache tree</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Zanthoxylum americanum</ScientificName>
    <Description>Aromatic, tree or shrub that can grow from 3' 3 3/8" - 26' tall.  The branches are dark brown and armed with 5/16" - 1/2" long prickles.  Trunk up to 6" diameter.  When broken, the twigs have a strong odor reminiscent of crushed lemon peel.</Description>
    <Leaves>3/8" - 12" long are composed of 5 to 11 ovate, pinnately arranged leaflets 1 9/16" - 3 1/8" long, 1/2 as wide.  The dark green and lustrous leaves are dotted with translucent glands.  The lower portion of the leaf is a lighter pubescent green beneath.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Brown or gray, zigzags, lemony smell when broke.  Paired spines.  The leaf buds 1/16" long are red and woolly.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Capsules 3/16" - 1/4".  Each fruit contains one seed.  The fruit ripens in late summer, turning from green to reddish brown.  When the seeds mature, they hang exposed from the split capsules.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray to brown, often with darker lines, smooth.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  Occurs along riverbanks and in moist ravines, thickets, and woods.  It is also found in somewhat drier areas such as upland rocky hillsides, bluffs, and open woods.</Range>
    <Remarks>The greenish-yellow flowers 1/8" wide appear in the spring before the leaves.  An infusion of the bark was used as a wash to treat itching skin and to treat swollen joints.  Infusions of the bark were taken internally for back pain, cramps, pulmonary problems, to treat fevers, and as a cold and cough remedy.  Infusions, made from the crushed roots, were also used to treat fevers.  Smoking the bark treated toothache.  Bark, either beaten or powdered was packed in and around an aching tooth.  Pieces of the bark were chewed to help breakup a tooth that was to be remove.  The fruits are eaten by a variety of birds and small mammals including bobwhite quails, vireos, pheasants, cottontails, and eastern chipmunks.  Bees are attracted to the flowers.  Giant swallowtail butterflies lay their eggs on the plants leaves.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonPricklyAsh/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonPricklyAsh/UpClose1.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonPricklyAsh/Buds.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonPricklyAsh/Seedling.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/CommonPricklyAsh/Seed.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>