<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Green Ash</Name>
    <OtherName>NA</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Fraxinus pennsylvanicus</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree with an open, irregular crown reaching about 50 feet in height.  Trunk up to 24" diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Opposite, pinnately compound, 4" - 6" long, 5 to 9 leaflets (usually 7), narrowly elliptical, long-pointed, bright green above, paler below.  Yellow in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Greenish-gray to reddish-brown with light colored lenticels (dots), often hairy, leaf scars straight or slightly notched top, reddish-brown to dark brown buds.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Straw-colored, one-seeded, winged (samaras), 1" - 2 1/2" long, borne in dense branching clusters.  Mature in early autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Brown to dark gray, smooth or slightly flaky; becoming deeply furrowed with narrow, interlacing ridges (diamond-shaped appearance).</Bark>
    <Range>Native to eastern North America and is fairly common west to Wyoming and Colorado along plains watercourses at elevations below 6,000 feet.  The tree is fast growing on moist bottomlands, and is extremely hardy to climatic extremes once established.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowers are inconspicuous, without petals, borne in dense clusters (panicles) near the ends of the twigs, male and female flowers on separate trees.  Windbreak: Plant green ash in the central rows of multi-row windbreaks.  It can also be used for single-row windbreaks, although loss of lower branches with age reduces effectiveness.  Wildlife: Green ash is of moderate importance to wildlife.  The winged seeds (samaras) are eaten by a number of birds and mammals including wild turkey and rodents.  Whitetail and mule deer browse the twigs and foliage.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/GreenAsh/UpClose1.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/GreenAsh/Buds.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/GreenAsh/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/GreenAsh/Leaves.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/GreenAsh/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>