<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Honey Locust</Name>
    <OtherName>Honey-shucks, Sweet-bean</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Gleditshia triacanthos</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree, growing to 70' tall, with an open crown, armed with thick-branched thorns to 8" long on the main trunk and lower branches.  Trunk often divided low, growing up to 36" diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, pinnately or bipinnately compound, 4" - 8" long, often with 3-6 pairs of side branches; leaflets paired, oblong, 1/8" - 1 3/16" long, shiny and dark green above, turning a showy yellow in the fall, typically dropping early.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Reddish brown, shiny, zigzags, often thory, 1" - 3" long, stiff, often 3-forked; lateral buds, brownish, small, 3 or more sunken in leaf scar.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Flattened and strap-like pods 6" - 16" long and 1" - 1 3/8" wide, dark brown at maturity, pendulous and usually twisted or spiraled, with a sticky, sweet, and flavorful pulp separating the seeds; seeds beanlike, about 3/8" long.  The common name "honey" is in reference to the sweet pulp of the fruits.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Blackish to grayish-brown, with smooth, elongate, plate-like patches separated by furrows.  Often with 2" - 8" thorns.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3b.  Midwestern in distribution, from the west slope of Appalachians to the eastern edge of Great Plains -- scattered in the east-central US from central Pennsylvania westward to southeastern South Dakota, south to central and southeastern Texas, east to southern Alabama, then northeasterly through Alabama to western Maryland.  Outlying populations occur in northwestern Florida, west Texas, and west central Oklahoma.  It is naturalized east to the Appalachians from South Carolina north to Pennsylvania, New York, and New England and Nova Scotia; sometimes a weed tree in India, New Zealand, and South Africa.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowers are greenish-yellow, fragrant, small and numerous in hanging clusters 2" - 5" long.  Honey-locust is widely planted as a hardy and fast-growing ornamental.  It is often used in extreme urban stress areas such as parking lot islands and sidewalk tree squares and has been planted for erosion control, for windbreaks and shelterbelts.  Because of the small leaflets and open crown, the trees cast a light shade that permits shade-tolerant turfgrass and partial-shade perennials to grow underneath.  Honey-locust wood is dense, hard, coarse-grained, strong, stiff, shock-resistant, takes a high polish, and is durable in contact with soil.  It has been used locally for pallets, crates, general construction, furniture, interior finish, turnery, firewood, railroad ties, and posts (fence posts may sprout to form living fences), but it is too scarce to be of economic importance.  The wood also was formerly valued for bows.  The geographic range of honey-locust probably was extended by Indians who dried the legumes, ground the dried pulp, and used it as a sweetener and thickener, although the pulp also is reported to be irritating to the throat and somewhat toxic.  Fermenting the pulp can make a potable or energy alcohol.  Native Americans sometimes ate cooked seeds, they have also been roasted and used as a coffee substitute.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Honeylocust/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Honeylocust/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Honeylocust/Leaves1.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Honeylocust/Bark.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Honeylocust/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>