<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Kentucky Coffeetree</Name>
    <OtherName>American coffee bean, American mahogany</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Gymnocladus dioicus</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium to large, tree reaching heights of 60' - 100' with a spread of 40' - 50'.  In open areas, the tree produces an open, rounded crown, but in native woods it grows to 75' with few branches.  Short trunk, 1' - 2 1/2' in diameter, divides into several large branches that end in contorted, stout twigs.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, bipinnately compound leaves, measuring from 1' - 3' in length by 18" - 24" in width, arranged in feather-fashion in 5 to 9 pairs of pinnae, the lowest are reduced to simple leaflets.  Typically the leaves consist of 6 to 14 entire; more or less ovate (almond shaped) leaflets, 2" - 3" long, acute, rounded or cuneate at the base, pubescent beneath when young, short petioled, and swollen at the base.   Leaves emerge late in the spring with a striking pink-bronze color, turning to a dark bluish-green above in summer.  Fall color is often a golden yellow, but the leaves drop early.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Stout, light brown to greenish-brown with whitish patches, somewhat zigzag or wavy, large heart shaped leaf scar, with a wide salmon-pink to brown colored pith.  </Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Flat, thick, woody legume 6" long, 1 1/2" wide, purplish brown; ripens in September or October and usually persists unopened on the tree until late winter or early spring. </SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Thick, dark bark is gray to grayish-brown, smooth; becoming marked with deep, irregular furrows and plates that curl at their sides.  Winter buds are small, reddish, and often placed above one another in close formation (superposed).  Terminal buds are absent.  The buds are small, downy, almost entirely imbedded in twigs, and surrounded by a hairy ring of bark.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3b.  Uncommon in its native habitat.  It can only be found in small colonies in temperate forests.  The natural range extends from New York and Pennsylvania west to Minnesota, southward to Oklahoma, and east to Kentucky and Tennessee. The species is also found in the Dakotas, Texas, Georgia, and the Carolinas; naturalized in Alabama, West Virginia, Virginia, and Delaware. It is believed to have been introduced into some areas by Native Americans.</Range>
    <Remarks>The greenish-white flowers appear in May and June, after the leaves.  The strong, heavy wood is used in general construction, cabinet work, sills, interior finish, fine furniture, railway sleepers, bridge timbers, crossties, fence posts and rails, and fuel wood.  Used for ornamental purposes in large area landscape plantings and parks.  In the fall, ripening pods contrast nicely with clear yellow fall foliage.  This pest free tree is an alternative to ash and elm where they have been ravaged by insects and disease.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/KentuckyCoffeetree/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/KentuckyCoffeetree/Fruit.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/KentuckyCoffeetree/Flower.png</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/KentuckyCoffeetree/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/KentuckyCoffeetree/Tree1.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>