<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Nannyberry</Name>
    <OtherName>Sheepberry, wild raisin, sweet viburnum</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Viburnum lentago</ScientificName>
    <Description>Multi-stemmed shrub or small tree that may reach 36' in height.  The plant is also known as “sheepberry” because its fruit smells like wet sheep wool when over ripe.  Nannyberry is leggy and somewhat open at maturity with an irregular to rounded crown.  Suckers often form at the base.</Description>
    <Leaves>Simple, opposite, and ellipse to egg-shaped with finely toothed margins.  They are 2" - 4” long and hairless, or nearly so, on both sides.  The 1/2" - 1” petiole has a wavy, mostly winged margin. Mature foliage is dark glossy green, becoming deep maroon to red in the fall.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Light green to gray-brown; terminal buds, brownish-gray, 2 scales, often fat and buld-shaped at base, long pointed tip.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  In hanging clusters, berry-like (a drupe), oval to nearly round, 3/8" - 9/16" long, changing from green to yellow, pink, rose and finally to blue-black, sweet and edible, with an odor of wet sheep wool when ripe and rotting, with a single, smooth, nearly flat stone.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Dark gray to black in a pattern of small blocks.  Skunklike odor when broken.</Bark>
    <Range>Across northeastern North America, from New Brunswick and Quebec to Saskatchewan, south to Colorado and Nebraska (rare), Missouri (extinct), West Virginia, and Pennsylvania, rare in the Appalachians in Maryland and Virginia and apparently disjunct in Georgia.</Range>
    <Remarks>Shade-tolerant species useful in landscape plantings as shrub borders, taller barriers, hedges, and windbreaks.  It produces good seasonal displays of flowers, fruits, and fall leaf color and the fruit are eaten by many species of birds and wildlife. Common habitats for nannyberry are low woods, swamp borders, and rich valleys at or near streambanks, usually in rich loam to clay-loam soil.  It also occurs in moist soil of wooded slopes and other upland sites, sometimes even in sandy or rocky soil.  It is a shade-tolerant understory shrub, but reaches relatively larger size in partial openings or along edges.  Flowering occurs in May-June and fruits in July–September.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Nannyberry/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Nannyberry/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Nannyberry/Leaves1.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Nannyberry/Fruit.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Nannyberry/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>