<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Northern Catalpa</Name>
    <OtherName>Indian bean tree, Indian cigar</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Catalpa speciosa</ScientificName>
    <Description>Large tree, 50' - 80' in height; conical or rounded crown.  The height at 20 years is about 20'.  Trunk diameter up to 24".</Description>
    <Leaves>Simple, large ovate to ovate-oblong, from 8" - 12" long, heart-shaped tropical looking without any lobes and are yellowish green in color.  Leaves are generally opposite on large branches and often whorled in 3 on young stems.  They turn an undistinguished yellow in the fall before dropping.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Twigs in winter have a unique identifying characteristic.  They have sunken leaf scars which resemble suction cups.  Their whorled arrangement of 3 scars per node is another trait easily identified.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Capsule.  Seedpods are slender and green in the summer growing from 10" - 24" long, looking similar to an exaggerated green bean.  They mature in the fall, turn dark brown, split open lengthwise to let seeds fall in the spring.  The whole pod is often blown off the tree.  The shape and color of the mature seedpod gives rise to the common name of cigar tree.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Ranges from scaly to ridged, to blocky plates.  On a mature tree trunk the bark may be from 3/4" to 1" thick, light grayish brown in color, and broken into longitudinal, scaly, flat ridges.  On young tree seedlings the bark is thin and easily damaged by impact, or rodents.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 4b.  Prior to European settlement it was native to a small area of the central Mississippi Valley basin, western Tennessee, north east Arkansas, the lowlands of south east Mississippi and southern Illinois and Indiana. Farmers once planted catalpas in groves to provide shade for hog lots.  It is now readily found from Kansas south to Texas and eastward to Louisiana.  It has been extensively propagated for over 200 years.  It can now be found in most eastern states, and planted to some extent in Europe and New Zealand.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowering takes place in late spring to early summer.  They occur as large clusters of showy, white, bell-shaped corollas of 5 lobes with ruffled edges and yellow, orange or purple interior spotting or streaking.  The name ‘catalpa’ comes from the Cherokee Indian language as the word for the tree. ‘Speciosa’ means “showy” for the large and numerous flowers.  Modern pharmaceutical research has shown catalpa trees have diuretic properties.  It is sometimes planted to attract the green catalpa worms, which are prized fish bait.  These caterpillars can be frozen and used as bait at a later time.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernCatalpa/UpClose1.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernCatalpa/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernCatalpa/Flower.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernCatalpa/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernCatalpa/Bark.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>