<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Ohio Buckeye</Name>
    <OtherName>Horse chestnut</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Aesculus glabra</ScientificName>
    <Description>Small tree most less than 49' tall, with a dense oval to round crown, branching quite low, usually on drier sites a thicket-forming shrub.  Trunk up to 24" diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Opposite, palmately compound, 4" - 15" long, leaflets 5 - 7, oval to obovate or lanceolate, 3" - 6" long, 1" 2 1/4" wide, with a finely toothed margin, emerging bright green, deepening to dark green, often developing yellow or orange fall color, emitting a strong fetid odor when crushed.  The leaves have a somewhat unique shape.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Thick, red-brown, hairy when young, with large triangular leaf scars; terminal buds large, orangish brown with keeled scales.  Bad odor when broken.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Rounded capsules about 1" - 2" wide, borne on a stout stalk, with a warty or prickly, thick, leathery husk; seeds: 1-2 smooth, glossy, chestnut-brown seeds, each with a pale scar (the “buck's eye”).</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Smooth and light gray, becoming rough and scaly.  Alligator like.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3b.  Primarily a species of the east-central US.  Var. glabra grows from western Pennsylvania, Ohio, and southern Michigan west to Illinois and south to Tennessee, Alabama, and rarely in Georgia, Mississippi, and states peripheral to the main northern range.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowers are creamy to greenish yellow, about 13/16" long, in large, showy, upright, branched, terminal clusters at ends of leafy branches.  Poisonous Plant: All parts of the plant (leaves, bark, fruit) are highly toxic if ingested – because of the glycoside aesculin, the saponin aescin, and possibly alkaloids.  Symptoms are muscle weakness and paralysis, dilated pupils, vomiting, diarrhea, depression, paralysis, and stupor.  Many landowners have eradicated it to prevent livestock poisoning.  Native Americans ground buckeye to use as a powder on ponds to stun fish.  The tree is an attractive ornamental, best in open, natural settings or parks because of its broad crown.  It also is sometimes cultivated as an ornamental shrub.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/OhioBuckeye/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/OhioBuckeye/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/OhioBuckeye/Fruit.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/OhioBuckeye/Flower.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/OhioBuckeye/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>