<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Red Maple</Name>
    <OtherName>Soft Maple, Swamp Maple, Carolina red maple</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Acer rubrum</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree, 40' - 70' tall, usually with a narrow compact crown, single-boled, or often in clumps of stems from one stump due to prolific sprouting.</Description>
    <Leaves>Deciduous, opposite, long-petioled, blades 2 1/2" - 4" long and usually about as wide, with 3 shallow short-pointed lobes, sometimes with two smaller lobes near the base, dull green and smooth above, lighter green or silvery beneath and more or less hairy.  Red leafstalk.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Bright red to reddish-brown with white lenticels (dots); buds, green or dark red, blunt.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Winged nutlets (samaras) in a pair, 1/2" - 1" long, clustered on long stalks, red to red-brown.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray and thin, becoming furrowed into long narrow scaly ridges on older trunks and branches.</Bark>
    <Range>Red maple is one of the most widely distributed trees in eastern North America, extending from Newfoundland and Nova Scotia west to southern Ontario, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Illinois, then south through Missouri, eastern Oklahoma, and southern Texas, and east to southern Florida.  Its distribution has been increased past its native range through broad cultivation and naturalization of the cultivated forms.</Range>
    <Remarks>The common name is in reference to the red twigs, buds, flowers, and fall leaves. Red maple has long been valued as an ornamental tree (shade, specimen, autumn accent, or wet site) because of its ease of establishment, rapid growth, brightly colored flowers and fruit, and fall leaf colors (ranging from clear yellow to orange to vivid red) displaying coloring during different seasons of the year. This tree is preferred over silver maple or boxelder when a fast growing maple is needed. The white, fine-grained wood is used for furniture, flooring, cabinetry, paneling, veneer, musical instruments, tool handles, cutting boards, butcher blocks, wooden bowls, boxes and crates, and many other uses. The sap of red maple is sometimes used for producing maple syrup.  Although its sap has only about half the sugar content as sugar maple (A. saccharum), the syrup tastes good. The seeds, buds and flowers are eaten by various wildlife species.  Squirrels and chipmunks store the seeds.  White-tailed deer, moose, elk browse red maple, and rabbits, which find the stump sprouts especially palatable, especially in fall and winter.  Cavities in red maples in river floodplain communities are often well suited for cavity nesters such as the wood duck and others.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/RedMaple/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/RedMaple/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/RedMaple/Flower.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/RedMaple/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/RedMaple/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>