<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Smooth Sumac</Name>
    <OtherName>Scarlet sumac</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Rhus glabra</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shrub or small tree growing up to 10'in height.  Smooth sumac forms thickets from root suckers.  The stems and branches are hairless and covered with a whitish waxy coating.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate and pinnately compound 11 13/16" - 19 11/16" long.  Smooth sumac has 11 - 31 leaflets, 2 3/4" - 3 9/16" long.  The leaflets taper to a point at the tip and are rounded at the base.  The margins are sharply serrated.  The upper surface is dark green and lustrous.  The lower surface is covered with a whitish waxy coating.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>The stems and branches are hairless and covered with a whitish waxy coating.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Drupes with a flattened globe shape, 1/8" - 3/16" long and are covered with red, sticky hairs.  The seeds are yellowish in color and smooth, 1/8" long.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Smooth and gray brown.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  Found in open woodlands, prairies, on dry rocky hillsides, and in canyons.</Range>
    <Remarks>Vigorously resprouts from rhizomes following fire.  The rhizomes are usually located between 3 and 12 inches below the soil surface and this may provide protection from heat during a fire.  The uses included the making of a root and leaf tea to treat diarrhea, dysentery, and mouth/throat ulcers.  The leaves of the plant were smoked for asthma.  The blossoms were used by the Chippewa in a mouthwash for teething children.  Comanche children enjoyed the sour acid taste of the fruits and leaves were added to tobacco for smoking by adults.  Dye was also created from various parts of the smooth sumac.  The fruits were used to make red dyes and the inner bark used to make yellow dyes.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SmoothSumac/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SmoothSumac/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SmoothSumac/Buds.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SmoothSumac/Fruit.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SmoothSumac/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>