<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Staghorn Sumac</Name>
    <OtherName>Rhus hirta</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Rhus typhina</ScientificName>
    <Description>Large shrub or small tree that can grow to 30' - 35' feet tall.  Irregular, flat crown; trunk up to 6" in diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, pinnately compound, 16" - 24" long.  The leaflets are narrowed or rounded at the base and sharply pointed at the tip with finely serrated edges; 11 - 31, 2" - 4 3/4" long, 3/4" - 1 1/2" wide.  The leaflets are dark green and smooth above, and pale beneath.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Brown, dense velvety brown hairs, very stout; lateral buds, small, cone-shaped, dark red with long hairs, mature in autumn.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Compact cluster of round, red, hairy fruits called drupes.  Each drupe measures 1/4" in diameter and contains one seed.  Each cluster of drupes may contain 100 to 700 seeds.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Dark brown to yellowish brown, smooth or slightly scaly.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 4a.  Found throughout the eastern half of the United States.  It generally prefers fertile, upland sites but tolerates a wide variety of conditions.  Sumac is tolerant of slightly acid soil conditions and textures ranging from coarse to fine.  Typical growing sites include open fields and roadsides, fence rows, railroad rights-of-way, and burned areas.  Sumac is not highly shade tolerate and are considered early successional species.</Range>
    <Remarks>Sumac serves primarily as a winter emergency food for wildlife.  Ring-necked pheasant, bobwhite quail, wild turkey, and about 300 species of songbirds include sumac fruit in their diet.  It is also known to be important only in the winter diets of ruffed grouse and the sharp-tailed grouse.  Fox squirrels and cottontail rabbits eat sumac bark.  White-tail deer like the fruit and stems.  Sumac also makes good ornamental plantings and hedges because of the brilliant red fall foliage.  It is best used on drastically disturbed sites where pioneer species are desirable.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/StaghornSumac/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/StaghornSumac/Buds.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/StaghornSumac/Seedling.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/StaghornSumac/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/StaghornSumac/Trees.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>