<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>White Ash</Name>
    <OtherName>Biltmore ash, Cane ash</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Fraxinus americana</ScientificName>
    <Description>Growing 40' - 70' tall, maintaining a central leader (strong apical dominance) in youth with an even distribution of branches, developing a dense, conical or rounded crown at maturity.  The trunk up to 24" diameter is long, straight, and free of branches for most of its length (except when open grown).</Description>
    <Leaves>Deciduous, opposite, pinnately compound, 8" - 12" long, leaflets 5 - 9 usually 7, short-stalked, ovate to ovate-lanceolate or elliptic, acuminate, 2 3/4" - 5" long and 1" - 2" wide, sometimes with a few teeth near the tip, dark green and smooth above, whitish below.  Yellow or purple in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Green or purplish with scattered white lenticels (dots), leaf scars deeply notched or U-shaped at the top, dark brown buds.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Samaras 1" - 2" long, hanging in clusters, with a narrow wing extending about 1/3 - 1/4 of the way down the cylindrical body.  Mature in late summer.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Thick, greenish-gray becoming dark gray, with a uniform, diamond-shaped ridge and furrow pattern.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 4a.  White ash grows over most of eastern North America, absent only from the outer Atlantic and Gulf coastal plains.  It occurs from Nova Scotia west to eastern Minnesota and south to Texas and northern Florida, northward barely into southern Quebec and Ontario.  It is cultivated in Hawaii.</Range>
    <Remarks>Flowers are numerous, very small, green to purplish, in small branched clusters near the branch tips, usually either male (staminate) or female (pistillate), a single tree usually bearing only one sex (the species dioecious).  This species flowers in April-May, the male first, before appearance of the leaves.  White ash is a good tree for open areas such as parks and campuses; it also is used as a lawn, shade, and street tree, even though its potential large size can make it incongruous with a small area.  Its use in wooden baseball bats is famous.  The wood is also used in furniture, doors, veneer, antique vehicle parts, railroad cars and ties, canoe paddles, snowshoes, boats, posts, ties, and fuel.  White ash is the most valuable timber tree of the various ashes.  White-tailed deer and cattle browse white ash and beaver, porcupine, and rabbits may eat the bark of young trees.  The seeds are eaten by wood duck, northern bobwhite, turkey, grouse, finches, grosbeaks, cardinals, fox squirrel, mice, and many other birds and small mammals.  The tendency of white ash to form trunk cavities makes it valuable for cavity nesters such as redheaded, red-bellied, and pileated woodpeckers.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteAsh/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteAsh/UpClose1.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteAsh/Leaves.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteAsh/Seed.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteAsh/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>