<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>White Walnut</Name>
    <OtherName>Butternut</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Juglans cinerea</ScientificName>
    <Description>Small to medium-sized tree growing 40' - 60' tall, with stiff upright branches and a wide-spreading crown, the young twigs, stems, and leaflets have hairs sticky-oily to the touch.  Trunk up to 24" diameter often divided.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, pinnately compound, 15" - 25" long; the leaflets 11-17, ovate to lanceolate or oblong-lanceolate, mostly 2" - 4 5/16" long, with finely toothed margins, terminal leaflet present, the lower surfaces densely covered with stellate hairs.  Yellowish-green; yellow or brown in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Greenish gray to reddish brown, rough, hairy, stout, finely chambered pith thats dark brown in color.  Bundle scars in 3 U-shaped clusters on leaf scar; buds, brownish, 1/2" - 3/4" long, fuzzy.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Oblong-ovoid nut 1 9/16" - 2 3/8" long, single or in clusters of 2 - 5, with a hard,thick, deeply furrowed shell enclosed by a thick husk with a sticky-glandular surface.  The nuts usually remain on the tree until after leaf fall.  The common name refers to the mature nut kernels, which are sweet and oily, like butter.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Brownish-gray, thick, shallowly divided into smooth or scaly plates.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 4a.  Primarily a species of the northeastern and north-central US and southern Canada from southeastern New Brunswick to Ontario and Quebec; in the US in Minnesota to Missouri and eastward through Tennessee into North Carolina and Virginia, with disjunct outlyers in Arkansas, Mississippi, Alabama, South Carolina, and Georgia.  It is uncommon throughout most of its range and formally listed as rare in many of the states in which it occurs.</Range>
    <Remarks>Light colored wood that cuts and carves easily.  Used for furniture, cabinetry, instrument cases, interior woodwork, including hand-carved wall panels and trim, and church decoration and altars.  Often planted close to the house on farmsteads for their use as food.  Kernels were used in baking and cultivars have been selected for nut size and for ease of cracking and extracting kernels.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteWalnut/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteWalnut/UpClose1.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteWalnut/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteWalnut/Fruit.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/WhiteWalnut/Leaves.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>