<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Jack Pine</Name>
    <OtherName>Banks Pine after Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820)</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Pinus banksiana</ScientificName>
    <Description>Small to medium-sized, native, evergreen tree averaging 55' - 65' high.  Crown small, irregulary rounded or spreading and flattened irregular.  Branches descending to spreading-ascending, poorly self-pruning.</Description>
    <Leaves>Evergreen, 3/4" - 1 1/2" long, and two twisted, divergent needles per fascicle, yellow-green in color all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex acute to short-subulate.  Fascicle sheath is short 1/8" - 3/16", semipersistent.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Branchlets are yellow to greenish-brown when young, then turning gray-brown with age; very resinous buds.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Seed Cone: 1" - 2" long, curved toward twig, open or closed scales.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Trunk straight to crooked; bark at first dark and scaly, later develops scaly ridges.</Bark>
    <Range>Jack pine occurs in Canada from British Columbia to Nova Scotia; and in the United States from Minnesota/Illinois eastward to New Hampsire, and Maine.</Range>
    <Remarks>Canadian Indians used Jack pine wood as frames in their canoes.  Pulpwood, constructions lumber, telephone poles, fence posts, mine timbers, and railroad ties.  Also used as Christmas trees.  Serves as habitat and breeding area for the endangered Kirtlan's warbler, federally endangered bird.  White-tailed deer browse saplings and young trees and snowshoe hares feed on young seedlings.  Porcupines feed on bark that often leads to deformed trees.  Red squirrels, chipmunks, mice, goldfinches, and robins consume seeds.  The minimum seed-bearing age of open-grown jack pine is 3-5 years old.  Some seed is produced every year and serotinous cones accumulate in the crown.  A mature stand of jack pines may have as many as 2 million seeds per acre stored in unopened cones.  The serotinous cones are sealed closed with a resinous bond that requires high temperatures to open and liberate the seeds.  This heat is usually provided by fire.  Because temperatures required to open cones typically occur in the warmest part of the summer, survival of new germinant may be poor because of drought conditions or lack of time to become established before winter.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Coniferous/Trees/JackPine/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Coniferous/Trees/JackPine/UpClose2.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Coniferous/Trees/JackPine/SeedCone.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Coniferous/Trees/JackPine/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Coniferous/Trees/JackPine/Tree2.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>