<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Black Cherry</Name>
    <OtherName>Wild Cherry/Rum Cherry</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Prunus serotina</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium to large tree up to 100' tall and 2' wide.  Many times has a leaning trunk with a round crown.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, simple, oblong, 2" - 6" long and 1 1/2" wide.  Fine toothed margins, glossy, green, white/red hairs on bottom midrib/base.  May have red/black glands (dots) near base.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red/brown, gray/purple, may have white lenticels (dots), smells like bitter almonds when broken/crushed.  Buds red/brown with 3 or more scales, that overlap like shingles.  Raceme 3 1/2" - 6" long on end of leafy twig.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Drupe, 1/4" - 1/2" in diameter.  Red/purple, mature in late summer.  Single seed.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Red/brown, thin, smooth, with horizontal ridges and plates.  Becoming dark and scaly.  Inner bark may smell bad.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3b.  Black cherry is a shade-intolerant species that primarily occurs in successional vegetation or in forest openings as well as in old fields and along fencerows.  It usually occurs as scattered individuals in various types of mesic woods and second-growth hardwood forests; at elevations of 0-1520 meters.  Black cherry in the southwestern US is confined to canyons, valleys, and rich bottomlands.  Flowering: May-July (March-April in the Southwest); fruiting: June-October.</Range>
    <Remarks>Black cherry wood is a rich reddish-brown color and is strong, hard, and close-grained – one of the most valued cabinet and furniture woods in North America.  It is also used for paneling, interior trim, veneers, handles, crafts, toys, and scientific instruments.  The fruit has been used to flavor rum and brandy (“cherry bounce”).  Pitted fruits are edible and are eaten raw and used in wine and jelly.  Black cherry fruits are important food for numerous species of passerine birds, game birds, and mammals, including the red fox, black bear, raccoon, opossum, squirrels, and rabbits.  Very large amounts of black cherry pose the theoretical risk of causing cyanide poisoning.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackCherry/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackCherry/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackCherry/Flower.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackCherry/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/BlackCherry/Tree1.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>