<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Boxelder</Name>
    <OtherName>Manitoba Maple</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Acer negundo</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree growing 30' - 50' tall, with broad rounded crown, trunk up to 36" diameter; usually developing a shallow, fibrous root system.</Description>
    <Leaves>Opposite, 4" - 9" long, pinnately compound with 3-5 (rarely 7 - 9) leaflets, 2" - 4" long and 1" - 2 1/2" wide, long-pointed, coarsely toothed and often shallowly lobed.  Pale green, yellow in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Green to purple with a whitish film that rubs off easily.  Bad odor when broken.  Buds white with reddish scales, fuzzy.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Winged nutlets (samaras) in a pair, 1" - 1 1/2" long, clustered on long stalks.  Mature in autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Light gray-brown with shallow fissures, becoming deeply furrowed with orangish troughs and warty ridges.</Bark>
    <Range>Boxelder is the most widely distributed of all American maples – its native range extends from the east coast of the U.S. to California, and from Alberta to southern Mexico and Guatemala.  The range is relatively continuous in the eastern U.S., but broken into small areas in the West and toward Central America.  It has become naturalized in areas far outside of its native range, including Europe.</Range>
    <Remarks>The flowers are yellow-green, about 2" long, the male (staminate) flowers fascicled, the female (pistillate) flowers in drooping racemes; most trees are either male or female (the species is essentially dioecious), but bisexual flowers occur on a few trees (technically polygamo-dioecious).  The wood of Boxelder is light, soft and weak, and of low commercial value.  It is used for pulp and rough lumber, usually mixed with other bottomland species, and has been used for boxes and crates, low-quality furniture, and interior finishing.  Boxelder produces sap high in sugar content and can be used to produce syrup sometimes called "mountain molasses."  Native Americans used the cambium for food, boiled down the sap for syrup and candy, and made a tea from the inner bark to induce vomiting.  The new branches were used to make charcoal for ceremonial painting.  Boxelder is natively a tree of river bottoms and disturbed sites on heavy, wet soils, often seasonally flooded (up to 30 days).</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Boxelder/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Boxelder/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Boxelder/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Boxelder/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Boxelder/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>