<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Eastern Pin Oak</Name>
    <OtherName>NA</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Quercus palustris</ScientificName>
    <Description>Large tree with heights ranging from 70' - 90' with diameters between 2' - 3'.  Distinguished by symmetric, pyramidal crown and its nearly round acorn that has a shallow, saucerlike cup.</Description>
    <Leaves>3" - 5" alternate leaves have 5 to 7 points or lobes with bristled tips and deep C-shaped sinuses.  The leaves change in color from a dark green to a deep scarlet red in fall.  The leaves are deciduous but will usually persist on the tree into winter.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>The lower branches of pin oak are prostrate to descending, with smooth, slender, reddish-brown twigs.  Clusters of pointed buds are located at the tips of twigs.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Acorns that are roundish, short stalked, 3/8" - 1/2" long, and capped with a thin and shallow saucer-like cup.  The acorns will take 16 - 18 months to develop from pollination to maturity.  When mature the acorn turns light brown to reddish-brown, and will drop from September to November.  In 30 to 35 year old stands of pin oak, 4,000 to 20,000 sound acorns per acre yields have been documented.  There are 410 acorns per pound.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Smooth, reddish to grayish-brown during the juvenile period, becoming darker and shallowly fissured as the tree growth slows with age.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 4a.  Native range spans from Rhode Island, Pennsylvania, Michigan, to Kansas south to North Carolina and northern Arkansas.  This tree grows under a wide range of site conditions, but is a true bottomland tree.  It is seldom found growing above elevations of 800 feet, or on sloped ground.  Pin oak grows in practically pure stands with good growth rates on wet, shallow sites with heavy soils that drain poorly.  On better quality sites it will often grow larger, but is normally out competed by other species.</Range>
    <Remarks>Even though the wood is heavy, strong, and hard, pin oak is typically used for fuel wood, wood pulp, and railroad ties, since it tends to warp.  Due to this species’ form, adaptability, growth rate, longevity, and fall foliar display, it is popular for ornamental usage.  Pin oak is utilized by many game species, especially wood ducks, white-tail deer, and wild turkey.  Due to its use by these highly sought after animals, pin oak is commonly planted for food plots.  The flowers of pin oak emerge soon after new leaves unfold in spring (April to mid-May).</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/EasternPinOak/UpClose2.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/EasternPinOak/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/EasternPinOak/Leaves1.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/EasternPinOak/Fruit.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/EasternPinOak/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>