<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Hackberry</Name>
    <OtherName>Beaverwood/False Elm/Nettle Tree/Sugar Berry</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Celtis occidentalis</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shrub to large tree up to 100' tall.  Drooping branches give it a cylindrical shape.  U-shaped crotch branches with a trunk up to 3' in diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, simple, 2 1/2" - 4" long and 1 1/2" wide.  Oval to lance shaped and look like elm, but are more pointed.  Sharp toothed margins, green turning yellow in autumn.  May have rough texture with warts.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red-brown with zigzag design.  Fine chambered white pith.  Buds are dark brown and may have hairs.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Small green drupes 1/4" - 1/3" in size, that change to dark red or black upon maturity in September and October.  May remain on the tree for several months after.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray or tan, corky warts and ridges, becoming scaly.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 3a.  Native to the United States.  It occurs from Maine and Quebec, west to North Dakota, Wyoming and Colorado, and south to Texas and Georgia.</Range>
    <Remarks>May live to be 200 years old.  Wild turkey, ring-necked pheasant, quail, grouse, lesser prairie chicken, cedar waxwing, robins, and other bird species consume common hackberry fruit, which persist throughout the winter.  Small mammals also consume the fruit.  Deer will browse common hackberry leaves in the absence of preferred browse species.  Common hackberry provides good cover for species such as mule deer, white-tailed deer, upland game birds, small non-game birds, and small mammals.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Hackberry/UpClose1.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Hackberry/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Hackberry/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Hackberry/Bark1.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Hackberry/Buds.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>