<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Iron Wood</Name>
    <OtherName>hop-hornbeam, Leverwood</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Ostrya virginiana</ScientificName>
    <Description>Small tree growing 20' - 50' tall with a trunk up to 12" in diameter.  Large and spacious crown of slender, spreading branches.</Description>
    <Leaves>Oblong-ovate, sharply doubly-serrate, and silky beneath, 2" - 4" in length and 1" - 2" in width.  Dark yellow-green, turning dull yellow in autumn.  May retain leaves into/or through the winter.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Brown to red-brown, slender, zigzags, willowy male catkins may be present in winter; buds, curvy, brown, with about 6 green scales.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Nutlet, enclosed in a puffy paper sac.  4 - 10 nutlets grouped in 2" - 4" long, funnel-shaped catkin that some say resembles hops.  Beer is good.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Brownish, scaly, narrow ridges or strips that may spiral around the trunk.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 3b.  Hop hornbeam is a small understory tree found in a variety of forested environments and openings located in the eastern United States and southern Canada.   It can also be found in the mountains of Mexico, south to northern South America.</Range>
    <Remarks>The wood of hop hornbeam is hard and durable.  It is used for fence posts, fuel, and tool handles.  The bark and inner wood was used to treat toothache, sore muscles, coughs, and many other ailments by American Indians.  This tree is used in landscaping, particularly along boulevards.  Its appeal is that it retains its coppery-tan leaves well into or through winter.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Ironwood/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Ironwood/Flower.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Ironwood/Fruit.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Ironwood/Bark.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/Ironwood/Tree.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>