<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Northern Pin Oak</Name>
    <OtherName>Hill's oak/jack oak</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Quercus ellipsoidalis</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree growing to 69' tall, with an irregularly rounded crown and low-hanging lower branches that persist as dead stubs, giving a ragged appearance to the trunk that grows to 18".</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, elliptic-obovate to elliptic-oblong, 3" - 5" long, 2 3/8" - 6" wide, with 5 – 7 bristle-tipped lobes broadest toward the tip, the sinuses rounded or elliptic and thumb-shaped, cut nearly 3/4 to the midvein, bright green above, with tufts of hairs in vein axils below, commonly turning red in fall.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red-brown; buds, red-brown, clustered at the twigs ends.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Acorn that is elliptic to broadly ovate, 1/2" - 13/16" long, the finely hairy cup enclosing 1/3 – 1/2 of the acorn and tapering to a stalk-like base.  Maturing in the second year.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Dark gray, smoothish, furrowed into narrow ridges on lower trunk and older branches.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 3b.  Distributed primarily in the middle and western parts of the Great Lakes region -- from central Michigan east to noth-central Wisconsin, eastern Iowa, northern Illinois, and northern Indiana.  Disjunct populations occur in northern Ohio, Arkansas, and extreme southeastern North Dakota.</Range>
    <Remarks>Northern pin oak is distinguished from pin oak by its more tapering and elongated acorns and its preference for drier habitats.  The leaves are shed in the autumn, whereas those of pin oak persist into the winter.  Northern pin oak acorns are eaten by a variety of wildlife species including gray squirrels, white-tailed deer, and blue jays.  Trunk cavities are utilized as nesting sites by wood ducks, eastern kingbirds, and the federally endangered Kirtland's warbler.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernPinOak/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernPinOak/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/NorthernPinOak/Tree.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>NA</Pic4>
    <Pic5>NA</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>