<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Shagbark Hickory</Name>
    <OtherName>Common hickory</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Carya ovata</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shagbark hickory is a medium to large deciduous tree which commonly grows to 60' - 80' in height and up 20" in diameter.  On favorable sites, trees may grow to 131' or more in height and reach up to 9' 8" in diameter.  Open-grown plants are characterized by an oblong crown, whereas those growing in forested areas tend to have a straight, slender columnar crown.  The shaggy gray bark exfoliates in long platelike strips.  Shagbark hickory has a deep taproot.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, pinnately compound, 8" - 14" long; leaflets, 5-7 (usually 5), upper 3 larger than lower 2, finely toothed margins, dark yellowish-green; golden yellow in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Gray to reddish brown with whitish hairs, stout, bundle scars scattered on leaf scar or arranged in a monkey face pattern, star shaped pith; terminal buds, large, egg shaped, loose scales.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Nut, 1" - 1 1/2" diameter, oval; thick, 4-ribbed husk; mature in autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray, smooth; becoming shaggy in appearance, long curved strips that are loosely attached.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to zone 4b.  Shagbark hickory occurs throughout most of the eastern North America but is largely absent from the southeastern and Gulf coastal plains and the lower Mississippi Delta.  It is found from southeastern Nebraska and southeastern Minnesota eastward through southern Ontario and Quebec to Maine and extends southward to Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, and eastern Texas.  Disjunct populations have been reported in the mountains of northeastern Mexico.</Range>
    <Remarks>Wood is tough, heavy, hard, and resilient.  Used for furniture, flooring, tool handles, dowels, ladders, and sporting goods.  Excellent fuelwood, because of high heat value and burns evenly.  Can be used as charcoal and gives food a hickory-smoked flavor.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/ShagbarkHickory/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/ShagbarkHickory/Bark.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/ShagbarkHickory/Buds.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/ShagbarkHickory/Tree.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/ShagbarkHickory/Tree1.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>