<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Speckled Alder</Name>
    <OtherName>Gray alder, hoary alder, swamp alder</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Alnus rugosa</ScientificName>
    <Description>Shrub growing to 30' tall with a trunk, that may be curved or bent; up to 6" in diameter.  Thicket forming; open crown.</Description>
    <Leaves>Elliptic to ovate, 1 1/2" - 4 3/4" long, 1 3/16" - 3 1/8" wide, broadest near or below middle, doubly and irregularly toothed, with 9-12 nearly straight, parallel veins on each side, with a ladder-like network of depressed veins, dull dark green above; turning yellow-brown in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red-brown having white spots or lenticels, three-way relationship shaped pith, willowy male catikins may be present in winter; buds red-brown, placed on small stalk, 2 sometimes 3 scales.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Nutlet, pincone shaped, 1/2" - 5/8" long catkin that may remain intact after release of fruits in spring.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Gray, red, or brown, thin and smooth, becoming broken into irregular plates, often with white lenticels/spots; that some say are for gas exchange.</Bark>
    <Range>Over much of the eastern two-thirds of Canada and reaches into Alberta, British Columbia, Mackenzie, and Yukon.  In the GREAT U.S. OF A, it reaches into the Lake States and Northeast and as far south as Iowa, West Virginia, Maryland, and Virginia.</Range>
    <Remarks>Provide cover for moose, white-tailed deer, rabbits, and others.  Moose, muskrats, beavers, and rabbits browse the twigs and foliage.  Songbirds, including redpolls, goldfinches, woodcock, and grouse eat the seeds, buds, and catkins.  Beavers build dams and lodges with speckled alder.  Tea was made from alder to cure diarrhea and toothaches.  Speckled alder’s acceptance of a wide variety of soil types makes it a good choice for disturbed site rehabilitation.  This is a valuable species to plant along stream banks for erosion controlMost new stems in alder stands are formed through sprouting from rhizomes, which may result in dense, clonal thickets.  Such sprouting is independent of aboveground stem damage, but root crown sprouts may contribute strongly to regeneration following top-kill from fires.  Sprouting rhizomes are usually within about 5 centimeters of the soil surface.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SpeckledAlder/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SpeckledAlder/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SpeckledAlder/Hairy.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SpeckledAlder/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SpeckledAlder/Flower.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>