<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Swamp White Oak</Name>
    <OtherName>Swamp oak</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Quercus bicolor</ScientificName>
    <Description>Meduim tree commonly growing to 50' - 65' tall, the lateral branches relatively slow in self-pruning, with an open, irregularly shaped crown.  Trunk up to 3' in diameter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, obovate to narrowly elliptic or narrowly obovate, 4" - 7" long, 2" - 4 1/2" wide, usually with regularly spaced, shallow, rounded teeth, or toothed in distal half only, or moderately to deeply lobed, upper surfaces dark green and glossy, lower surfaces lighter green to whitish, softly hairy.  Red to brown-orange in autumn.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Light brown to red-orange; buds, light brown to orange-brown, cluster at twig ends.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Acorn that is ovoid-ellipsoid or oblong, mostly 9/16" - 1 3/16" long, single or clustered in groups of 2 – 4, on a stalk (peduncle) 1 3/16" - 3 1/8" long; cup enclosing 1/3 – 1/2 of the acorn, scales closely appressed, finely grayish tomentose, those near rim of cup often with a short, stout, irregularly recurved spinose tip.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Light brown becoming dark gray; scaly or flat-ridged, often peeling off in large, ragged, papery curls.</Bark>
    <Range>Hardy to Zone 4a.  Occurs mainly in the Midwestern states from Iowa, Missouri, eastern Kentucky, and southern Wisconsin east to New York, Pennsylvania, Connecticut, and Massachusetts.  Isolated populations occur northward in Minnesota, other New England states, and Quebec and Ontario, and southward to Tennessee, Virginia, and North Carolina.</Range>
    <Remarks>The wood is used for furniture, cabinets, veneers, interior finishing, and flooring, as well as for boxes, crates, fence posts, railroad ties, and beams and boards for general construction.  The trees can grow well in areas that are dry, poorly drained and wet, or even occasionally flooded, and they will tolerate significant soil compaction.  The acorns are sweet and are an important food for wildlife such as squirrels, mice, white-tailed deer, beaver, black bear, and a variety of birds, including ducks and turkey.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SwampWhiteOak/UpClose1.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SwampWhiteOak/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SwampWhiteOak/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SwampWhiteOak/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/SwampWhiteOak/Fruit.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>