<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Trembling Aspen</Name>
    <OtherName>Quaking aspen/Mountain aspen</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Populus tremuloides</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium/large tree fast growing 40' - 90' tall and 2' wide.  Narrow, cone shaped becoming open and round.</Description>
    <Leaves>Simple, alternate, round/egg shaped.  2" - 6" long and 1" - 2 1/2" wide.  Fine toothed margins.  Yellow/blue green turning yellow in autumn.  May have flat leafstalk.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Red/brown with orangeish lenticels (dots).  Glossy with a star-shaped pith.  Buds are red/brown, skinny, and pointy.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Capsule, with many seeds that may have cotton like hairs.  3" - 4" catkins maturing in late spring.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Smooth, green/white to gray/white, thin and peeling, becoming thicker and furrowed with age, especially toward the base.</Bark>
    <Range>Trembling aspen is the most widely distributed tree species in North America.  It grows from Alaska across the Northwest Territories to Quebec and Newfoundland, south to West Virginia and Virginia, and in all of the western North America US states (except Oklahoma and Kansas) --  in all Canadian provinces and all but 13 US states (absent from the Southeast).  It occurs in both the eastern and western sierras of Mexico, into the south-central part of the country.</Range>
    <Remarks>Aspen stands are good firebreaks, often dropping crown fires in conifer stands to the ground when they reach aspens and even sometimes extinguishing the fire because of the small amount of flammable accumulation.  They allow more ground water recharge than do conifer forests and they also play a significant role in protecting against soil erosion.   They have been used in restoration of riparian habitats.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/TremblingAspen/UpClose1.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/TremblingAspen/Leaves.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/TremblingAspen/Bark.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/TremblingAspen/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/TremblingAspen/Trees.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>