<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Definitions>
  <Def>
    <Name>Yellow Birch</Name>
    <OtherName>Gray birch, swamp birch</OtherName>
    <ScientificName>Betula alleghaniensis</ScientificName>
    <Description>Medium tree growing 50' - 70' tall, with straight trunks and variable crowns.  Trunk up to 36" in diamter.</Description>
    <Leaves>Alternate, simple, narrowly ovate to broadly oblong, 2 1/8" - 4" long, base rounded to cuneate or cordate, margins sharply doubly toothed, apex acuminate, usually softly hairy beneath along major veins and in vein axils, often with scattered, minute, resinous glands.</Leaves>
    <Twigs>Green-brown to yellowish brown with raised, white dots. Odor and taste of wintergreen, usually with small resinous glands.  Buds, light red-brown, sharply pointed and hairy.</Twigs>
    <SeedConeOrFruit>Fruit:  Nutlet, winged.  Nutlet is in tight group in an erect, 3/4" - 1" long catkin that is mature in early autumn.</SeedConeOrFruit>
    <Bark>Bronze to yellow-brown, smooth and shiny, usually separating into thin layers, giving a shaggy appearance.</Bark>
    <Range>Yellow birch ranges from Newfoundland, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Anticosti Island west through southern Ontario to extreme southeastern Manitoba; south to Minnesota and northeastern Iowa; east to northern Illinois, Ohio, Pennsylvania to northern New Jersey and New England; and south in the Appalachian Mountains to eastern Tennessee and northeastern Georgia.</Range>
    <Remarks>The wood of yellow birch is heavy, strong, close-grained, even-textured, and shows a wide color variation, from reddish brown to creamy white.  It is used for furniture, cabinetry, charcoal, pulp, interior finish, veneer, tool handles, boxes, woodenware, and interior doors.  The wood can be stained and takes a high polish.  Yellow birch is one of the principal hardwoods used in the distillation of wood alcohol, acetate of lime, charcoal, tar, and oils. Deer consume large numbers of yellow birch seedlings in summer and prefer green leaves and woody stems in fall.  Moose, white-tailed deer, and snowshoe hare also browse yellow birch.  The seeds are eaten by various songbird species, and ruffed grouse feed on seeds, catkins, and buds.  Red squirrel cut and store mature catkins and eat the seeds.  Beaver and porcupine chew the bark.</Remarks>
    <Pic1>Images/Deciduous/Trees/YellowBirch/UpClose.jpg</Pic1>
    <Pic2>Images/Deciduous/Trees/YellowBirch/UpClose1.jpg</Pic2>
    <Pic3>Images/Deciduous/Trees/YellowBirch/Leaf.jpg</Pic3>
    <Pic4>Images/Deciduous/Trees/YellowBirch/Buds.jpg</Pic4>
    <Pic5>Images/Deciduous/Trees/YellowBirch/Trees.jpg</Pic5>
  </Def>
</Definitions>